<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The proceedings of the Grisons, in the yeere 1618 VVherein are truely and cleerely laid open the lawfull and vrgent causes of calling an assembly of the commons: and of their due proceeding and honourable prosecution of iustice, which they were enforced to vse against some false and perfidious patriots, in a full congregation, and with absolute power met together at Tosana. Imprinted and published by commandement of the lords the heads, the counsailours and commons of the three confederations of the renowned free states of the Grisons: in maintenance of the truth, and romoouing all manner of calumniation.</title>
            <title>Grawpündtnerische Handlungen des M.DC.XVII. Jahrs. English</title>
            <author>Graubünden (Switzerland)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12390</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103461</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839214</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839214</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1068:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The proceedings of the Grisons, in the yeere 1618 VVherein are truely and cleerely laid open the lawfull and vrgent causes of calling an assembly of the commons: and of their due proceeding and honourable prosecution of iustice, which they were enforced to vse against some false and perfidious patriots, in a full congregation, and with absolute power met together at Tosana. Imprinted and published by commandement of the lords the heads, the counsailours and commons of the three confederations of the renowned free states of the Grisons: in maintenance of the truth, and romoouing all manner of calumniation.</title>
                  <title>Grawpündtnerische Handlungen des M.DC.XVII. Jahrs. English</title>
                  <author>Graubünden (Switzerland)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. Purslowe for E. Blount],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Grawpündtnerische Handlungen des M.DC.XVII. Jahrs.</note>
                  <note>Includes articles of the league with Spain.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴ (-M4).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The proceeding of the Grisons. 1618.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Graubünden (Switzerland) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3617:1"/>
            <p>THE PROCEEDINGS OF THE GRISONS, IN THE YEERE 1618.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN ARE TRVELY and cleerely laid open the lawfull and vrgent cauſes of calling an Aſſembly of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons: and of their due proceeding and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable proſecution of Iuſtice, which they were enforced to vſe againſt ſome falſe and perfidious Patriots, in a full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and with abſolute power met together at TOSANA.</p>
            <p>IMPRINTED AND PVBLISHED BY Commandement of the Lords the Heads, the <hi>Counſailours and Commons of the Three Confe</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations of the Renowned Free States of the <hi>Griſons:</hi> in maintenance of the Truth, and remoouing all manner of calummation.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3617:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3617:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ee that will take an exact Suruey of the known World, beginning at home, and going as farre as Trauell &amp; Hiſtory can lead him, ſhall finde few people which are <hi>Aborigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls,</hi> and firſt Inhabitants of the Cities or Countries they now poſseſſe: But by ſettling of Collonies, or In-roads and Inundations of Warre, haue been tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted. The <hi>Saxons</hi> hither: the <hi>Cimbrians</hi> into <hi>France:</hi> the <hi>Gaules</hi> into <hi>Italy:</hi> the <hi>Vandalls</hi> into <hi>Spaine:</hi> the <hi>Greekes</hi> into the Kingdome of <hi>Naples:</hi> the <hi>Scythians</hi> into <hi>Turky:</hi> the <hi>Turks</hi> into <hi>Greece;</hi> And theſe <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> into this part of the <hi>Alpes,</hi> anciently called <hi>Rhetia,</hi> then <hi>Canninia;</hi> after, the vpper <hi>Sleſia;</hi> and now laſtly, in their own Language <hi>Growpijndter</hi> or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federations.</p>
            <p>This Countrey had the name of <hi>Rhetus,</hi> who ſled out of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> from the fury of the <hi>Gaules,</hi> in the yeere <hi>187.</hi> before the comming of Chriſt, and led with him many of the Inhabitants about <hi>Florence, Piſa,</hi> and <hi>Lucca,</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in theſe high &amp; in-acceſsible Mountaines: And as a few weather-beaten <hi>Troians</hi> laid the foundation of Great <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome few fugitiue Citizens of <hi>Vincen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za, Padoa,</hi> and other Townes in <hi>Lombardy</hi> (fleeing the rage of the barbarous <hi>Gothes,)</hi> planted themſelues in the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Mariſhes, where they firſt began the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned
<pb facs="tcp:3617:3"/>
               <hi>Venice:</hi> So this handfull of Tuſcans here plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and ſettling themſelues, are now growne to a warlike, ſtrong, and populous Nation. Such a fruitfull mother of children is <hi>Neceſſity,</hi> begotten by old <hi>Time</hi> their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that (as the mother of <hi>Cyrus</hi> dreamed) there ſprings a Vine in her wombe, by which in time whole Countries are ouer-ſhadowed.</p>
            <p>This Countrey lyeth betweene the Degrees <hi>46.</hi> and <hi>44.</hi> in Latitude: part in <hi>Germany,</hi> and part in <hi>Italy;</hi> diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Ridge of the Mountaine <hi>Splugen:</hi> On this ſide they ſpeake Dutch, on the other, Bergamaſque Italian. They haue free exerciſe of both Religions, Reformed and Romane. Here the Riuers of the <hi>Rhein</hi> and <hi>Teſin</hi> haue their heads; that, diuiding it ſelfe into ſeuerall Branches, and diſemboking into the <hi>German Ocean;</hi> this other falling into the <hi>Po,</hi> is carried by him into the <hi>Venetian Gulph.</hi> It confineth East vpon <hi>Tiroll,</hi> Weſt vpon the <hi>Swiſſe</hi>-Cantons, North vpon <hi>Conſtance, Friburg,</hi> and ſome parts of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and South vpon the Countrey of <hi>Bergamo</hi> and State of <hi>Millan.</hi> The hither part is Mountainous, and therefore not ſo well able to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine the Inhabitants; yet are there many fruitfull Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, which, (beſides their frugall and parſimonious maner of liuing) ſupply that want. Among theſe is <hi>Valtelina</hi> on the Italian ſide; for this is ſo plentifull of Corne, Cattle, Wines, &amp; other fruits, as any part of <hi>Europe.</hi> The chiefe Townes of this fruitfull Valley, are, <hi>Bormio, Sondrio,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:3"/>
Tirano, Poſclauio, Morbegno, Traona,</hi> and <hi>Telo,</hi> whereof the Valley takes the name, wherein are aboue <hi>100000.</hi> ſoules. The part on this ſide hath many Caſtles and Townes, whereof <hi>Coira</hi> is the chiefe. It ſtandeth vpon the Riuer <hi>Laſgar;</hi> it embraced the Chriſtian faith the yeere <hi>448.</hi> and in <hi>744.</hi> had many priuiledges granted by <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and the Biſhop thereof made Rector of <hi>Rhetia:</hi> Among other Liberties it hath the coyning of Money, which paſſeth currant through the whole Country.</p>
            <p>The nature and manners of this people may bee read by the Character of the <hi>Swiſſes:</hi> For, lying in the ſame Latitude, and inhabiting the like Mountaines, herein alſo they are like vnto them. A people giuen to Tillage and Planting their grounds; feeding vpon Butter, Cheeſe, Fiſh, Bread, Rootes, Wine, and but ſmall ſtore of Fleſh; vſing little Merchandize, but much manifacture, borne to Armes, and brought vp to labour; much addicted to exerciſe, eſpecially the Harquebuſe, hauing in diuers Townes and Villages Prizes for them which doe best. They are alſo much delighted with hunting in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, of wilde Goates, Bucks, Beares, Wolues, and wilde Boares: holding it a great honour to take of theſe Beaſts, and for a Trophey to naile their heads on their gates; for which alſo ſometime the State rewards them. They are (onely on this ſide the Countrey) ſubiect to the Swiſſe and Dutch fault of exceſsiue drinking.</p>
            <p>Their Countrey is diuided into three Cantons or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations.
<pb facs="tcp:3617:4"/>
The firſt is called, The Confederation of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè,</hi> or <hi>Ca-di-Dio:</hi> (that is, Gods Houſe:) the ſecond is, <hi>Lega Griſa:</hi> and the third, <hi>Lega delle Dritture,</hi> or Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdictions. <hi>Cadi Dio</hi> containes the City &amp; Territory of <hi>Coira,</hi> the Valley of vpper and lower <hi>Agnadina,</hi> with <hi>Bregaglia: Lega Griſa</hi> contains the Valley of <hi>Meſolce,</hi> and <hi>Calanca,</hi> with the Lands of <hi>Rogoret &amp; Muſocco,</hi> with other Valleys beſides, on this ſide the Ridge of the Mountaines: the <hi>Dritture</hi> containe the reſt of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. The firſt comprehendeth <hi>21.</hi> Comminalties or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations: the ſecond <hi>19.</hi> the third <hi>10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe three Cantons make the Confederation Generall: for though each of them haue their peculiar Magiſtrates, Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Iuſtice ciuill and criminall, yet the higheſt power and laſt Appeale is to the Senate or Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Three Cantons together: called by them the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach.</hi> Whereunto the firſt Confederation ſends <hi>23.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties or Commiſsioners: the ſecond <hi>28.</hi> and the third <hi>14.</hi> Where, they propound, conſult, and determine onely that, for which they haue direction and command from their ſeuerall Cantons. To this Senate likewiſe belongeth to treat and conclude Peace or Warre, to make or reuoke Alliances and Leagues, to eſtabliſh or abrogate Statutes and Lawes, to determine any difference betweene either of the Cantons, or reſolue any buſineſſe concerning the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall good of the whole Countrey. The places of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly are theſe; <hi>Coira</hi> in the firſt Confederation: <hi>Illian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:4"/>
in the ſecond: and <hi>Dauoſium</hi> in the laſt. But if the Three Confederations are to treat a Buſineſſe, which they would haue kept ſecret, there are onely admitted into Councell, the Conſull of <hi>Coira,</hi> the Prouinciall Iudge of the <hi>Lega Griſa,</hi> and the Amano or chiefe Iuſtice of the <hi>Dritture:</hi> yet the voice to confirme all, is that of the <hi>People;</hi> if there be any Appeale. For controuerſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues thus: If a difference ariſe betweene the Three Confederations, three or foure perſons out of each are deputed (with diſcharge of their Oath to their owne Confederation) to arbitrate and compound the buſineſſe. If two be at difference, the third determines it. If between any of the Comminalties, the Senate of all Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations ioyntly depute Iudges of the buſineſse. If be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a priuate man &amp; the Confederations, two or three Iudges are appointed out of euery ſeuerall Confederation. If two Confederations haue a difference with the third, ſixe of the two Confederations, and ſixe of the third are choſen for Iudges: and in caſe theſe agree not, one onely Iudge is choſen by the voice of all the Commons.</p>
            <p>The firſt League was made betweene the Biſhop of <hi>Coira,</hi> and the Prouinces about him, in the yeere <hi>1441.</hi> The next betweene the Abbot of <hi>Zizatis,</hi> the Count of <hi>Mauan,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Bezuns,</hi> with them of <hi>Coira;</hi> this was called <hi>Lega Griſa,</hi> as that former <hi>Lega Cadè:</hi> after this, the Comminalties of <hi>Segouia</hi> made League with the two former, and was called <hi>Lega delle Drit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:5"/>
And laſtly, in the yeere <hi>1470.</hi> they all Colleag<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But in the yeere <hi>1471.</hi> hauing difference with their neighbours of <hi>Tiroll,</hi> they all entred League with ſeuen Cantons of the <hi>Swiſſe.</hi> And laſtly, the whole thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Cantons of the <hi>Swiſſe,</hi> with theſe of the <hi>Griſon</hi> Confederation, and the ſeuen Wards or Sokes of the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſians,</hi> ioyned all in League with <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Gallo:</hi> which Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was firſt founded and inhabited by one <hi>Sengall</hi> a Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh-man, with other of his Countrey, and after grew to haue large Territories and Priuiledges. Thus all theſe Cantons <hi>Griſon</hi> and <hi>Swiſſe,</hi> with the <hi>Valeſians</hi> and them of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Gallo,</hi> being a great, Warlike, and powerfull Body, ſtand in the gates of <hi>Italy,</hi> as firme as the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wherein they liue, against any forraine force what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>A larger Relation might be made of this People and Countrey: But becauſe a great head holds no Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry with a ſmall Body; this little ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to giue light to the enſuing Declaration.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="proceedings">
            <pb facs="tcp:3617:5"/>
            <head>THE PROCEEDING OF THE <hi>GRISONS.</hi> 1618.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold benefits, and gracious fauours granted vs by God, the libertie of our Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-wealth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we order &amp; go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne our owne affaires, is not the leaſt: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the lawfull vſe and ſweet fruition thereof, our Soules &amp; Honours, Bodies and Goods, are freely enioyed and ſafely preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from all vexation and trouble. Hence is it, that <hi>Libertie</hi> like a moſt precious Iewell hath been ouer much endeared and deſired of all men.</p>
            <p>We therefore the Inhabitants of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:3617:6"/>
and high <hi>Rhetia,</hi> now called by the name of the three <hi>Griſon Confederations generall,</hi> hauing long enioyed the ſweet fruits and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of the bleſſings of God, and of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power, manifeſtly ſhewed in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fortitude and valour of our religious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors, who for many ages haue poſſeſſed and preſerued both thoſe liberties. It hath ſeemed moſt meet and requiſite to vs, the Heads, Counſellors, and Commons of both the free Religions of theſe our Countries, publikely and priuately to hold the ſame li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty much indeared, and highly prized, and as much as in vs lyeth, to continue it among vs, and to our poſteritie.</p>
            <p>We could well haue wiſhed that theſe our times had beene ſuch, as we might like our valiant forefathers, haue continued in the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient poſſeſſion of our owne, without any trouble or moleſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: But as al things of this world are ſubiect to declination and decay; ſo alſo this free State of ours is with time not a little weakened, and the danger thereof ſo much increaſed in theſe our dayes, as it had runne into manifeſt precipitation and ruine, had not God in his mercy ſtirred vp the zeale
<pb facs="tcp:3617:6"/>
of our faithfull and good Compatriots to tame and chaſtiſe the corrupters of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and withall to conſerue and ſettle it in the former freedome.</p>
            <p>We are therfore willing, for ſatisfaction of thoſe that deſire to know what hath paſſed, and are rather louers of the truth then ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, to giue them this full, ſubſtantiall, and true aduertiſement and accompt of what hath paſſed, not onely in the weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our State, and impayring of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but alſo in the lawfull proceeding and iuſt puniſhing of thoſe perfidious ones, for the reeſtabliſhment of our Gouernment, and reparation of thoſe Breaches they had made vpon the libertie of our Countrey.</p>
            <p>The forme of our Common-wealth is <hi>Popular,</hi> and the chooſing and diſplacing of the ſupreme Magiſtrate, Officers, Iudges, and Commiſſioners in our free Countries and of our Subiects, ſtandeth meerely in the power of our <hi>People,</hi> who haue abſolute au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie by pluralitie of voices, to eſtabliſh and abrogate Lawes, Leagues, and Affiances with Princes and forraine States, to make Warre or Peace, and to order and gouerne all
<pb facs="tcp:3617:7"/>
other buſineſſes belonging to the higher and lower Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>All theſe Liberties and Priuiledges of ours, ſome priuate Perſons through their great wealth and authoritie, with Penſions, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, Friendſhips, and Adherences, haue ſought to appropriate vnto themſelues, and aſſume into their owne hands, not once, but diuers times, and in ſeueral places, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalties, according as they haue had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: wherein their practices haue preuailed ſo farre, as not onely our free Patriots and Subiects, but euen Princes &amp; forrain States, whatſoeuer they deſired in our Common-wealth, they were forced to ſeeke it at their onely hands: towards whom theſe men v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all manner of treacheries, vnfaithfulneſs, falſ-hood, deceit, tyrannie, lewd practices, and violences; and among many other their abuſes, they haue brought our Countrey in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diſ-reputation and ſcandall with all Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and forraine States, by vnderraking high matters, and making great promiſes for large ſummes of money, and after through their perfidious tergiuerſation, haue falſely broken their faith, and wrought the multitude ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="tcp:3617:7"/>
one way, ſomtimes another, of whoſe ſimplicitie they made their vſe, and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ruled and ledde them to all their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</p>
            <p>And albeit this wofull eſtate of our affairs lay couered and hid as vnder a cloud, yet both the wiſer fort of men among vs, and the <hi>Commons</hi> alſo, made ſuch daily diſcouery of the badde effects thereof, as they all did much lament their miſerable eſtate, and would moſt willingly haue remedied ſo great a miſchiefe, by a preſent reformation &amp; lawfull proceeding: but they found no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible meanes to effect that fruitfully, which they deſired ſo earneſtly, by reaſon of the great and many adherents of theſe wicked men, and the diffidence and iealouſie that the common people had of all men. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon all the true-hearted and honeſt men of our Countrey, well ſeeing that our State could not long ſtand in theſe diſorders, and yet not knowing how to repaire or amend them, they haue ſent vp their ſighs &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to God, the true protector of the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: who hath now at laſt heard their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full complaint, and ſhewed them the way
<pb facs="tcp:3617:8"/>
to recouer their deliuery.</p>
            <p>And beſides thoſe many graue and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent perſons of the body Politike, diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the miſerable eſtate of our Affaires; our Church-men alſo haue both earneſtly and inceſſantly, priuately and publiquely, called vpon the State for a Reformation, and without any reſpect or feare of the danger they might incurre, they ioyntly preferred a Bill of Complaint, in the publique Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly held at <hi>Tauas</hi> in the month of Auguſt, 1617. laying open their grieuances before the Three Confederations generall, and the ordinary Magiſtrate, for theſe ſo great and ſo vnſupportable inconueniences: and after a long commemoration of the preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and dangers, they modeſtly and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly preſſed for a ſpeedy and neceſſary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, the Magiſtrates calling into conſideration the importance of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other waighty reaſons, reſolued to propound theſe gneuances to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellers &amp; Comminalties of the <hi>People,</hi> as to the ſupreme Magiſtrate, whom they ought and muſt obey: And accordingly in a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node
<pb facs="tcp:3617:8"/>
holden in April, 1618. by the Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Diuines, they drew a Bill (the ſame in ſubſtance with that former) to be offered to the Councellers and Comminalties ouer all their Churches, earneſtly requiring and humbly beſeeching, that a ſpeedy courſe might be taken by the States Generall, for remedy of ſo great an inconuenience, by all the faire wayes and ordinary meanes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, without tumult or diſturbance of the State, for the recouery of their liberty Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and Ciuill, and for their freeing from the treacherous Complots, and perfidious Treaties, which ſome of our men haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained with diuers Princes, and forraine States: yet ſo, as not to prouoke theſe men to indignation, deſpight, or wicked deliberati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but rather to carry the buſineſſe with ſuch temper and moderation, that as the faithfulneſſe &amp; integrity of our fore-fathers is honoured and magnified by vs, ſo ours to our poſterity might be recommended. And though this our endeuourſ to a milde and quiet proceeding hath beene publiſhed and made knowne to the world; yet the chiefe heads of that corruption haue laboured
<pb facs="tcp:3617:9"/>
with all their might, to croſſe our deſeignes, to turne all to ſmoake, and to continue in their former practices and violent inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: Hereupon they of the Clergie haue with more vehemency vrged and preſſed in their Sermons for a generall reformation of the State; and that the people would make choyce of ſome honourable Perſons of the Country, ſuch as were vnpaſſionate, and free from any intereſt or engagement with other Princes or States; to whom they might lay open the notorious perfidie of ſome men tyranniſing amongſt them, as an inſolency no longer to be endured, and the principall cauſe of hindering the intended Reformation.</p>
            <p>Into this number, the Adherents and Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of theſe treacherous and malicious men, preſently intruded, forcing themſelues by all poſſible meanes, to hinder and make fruſtrate all the good effects by good men deſired. Whereupon the people deſpairing to bring the buſineſſe to any wiſhed yſſue by ſo ſmall a number of perſons deputed, and finding that theſe tyranniſers ouer the State could no wayes be ouer-topped, but
<pb facs="tcp:3617:9"/>
by a greater number, they proceed (not by way of reſiſtance and force) but by plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of voices, and by excluſion of all ſorts of corruptions and falſe inſinuations.</p>
            <p>To which purpoſe the fiue Comminalties of the lower <hi>Agnadina</hi> lying vnder the <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſna,</hi> with thoſe of <hi>Munſtertal,</hi> met together in the end of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt, earneſtly by their let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſolliciting all the other Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minalties and Deputies of the Three Confederations to do the like, and iointly to aſſiſt them as a people oppreſſed and afflicted, their ancient power and authority being wreſted from them, and engroſſed and vſurped by certaine priuate perſons; their voices falſified, their Lawes changed, and their goods daily and vnduly taken from them, vnder pretext of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracie &amp; Iuſtice; to the end the new Lawes might be abrogated, their ancient Countrey reſtored to the former libertie, the Treaſures of Princes and States forraine might not bee ſeazed vpon by priuate perſons, without the knowledge and conſent of the People; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that Princes might be no more abuſed and entertained with their falſe promiſes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious treachery, but that a lawfull and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial
<pb facs="tcp:3617:10"/>
Court of Iuſtice might be eſtabliſhed by the whole Countrey, for the puniſhment of theſe their tranſgreſſions formerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, &amp; for the defence of all true-hearted and honeſt Compatriots.</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe inſtant intreaties and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, there ioined preſently with them cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Comminalties of the Iuriſdictions, &amp; of the <hi>Cade,</hi> with Enſignes diſplay de, and a great number of men, namely, they of the higher <hi>Agnadina, Pregello, Poſclauia, Firſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau,</hi> and <hi>Berguno,</hi> reſoluing to aſſiſt their neighbours in the reformation of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like State, and eſtabliſhing a lawfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Court of Iuſtice, againſt theſe trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Delinquents to their common coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; ſo that this proceeding might ſtand with the good liking &amp; approbation of the other Comminalties. While this is in Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>Rodulphus Planta</hi> chiefe head of the tyrannizing faction dwelling at <hi>Zernes,</hi> in the lower <hi>Agna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina</hi> vpon <hi>Waltaſna,</hi> (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the ſafe-conduct which the people granted to him and his Enſignes) by aduice and counſaile of his adherents, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies himſelfe with men and munition in his
<pb facs="tcp:3617:10"/>
houſe, and Tower anciently called <hi>Wilden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> placing there in Garriſon and in the ſtreets of <hi>Zernes</hi> 600. of his men, all good ſouldiers, taking an oath of them to defend him, to keepe the paſſages, throwe downe the Bridges, and to make open and hoſtile warre againſt the Confederats and his neere neighbours. He hath alſo demanded milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſuccours from others, thereby to drawe a ciuill Warre vpon his owne Countrey: but they of <hi>Cade</hi> comming to aſſaile his houſe, and hee doubting leſt his men might be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to render vp the Place and him in it, as not being able to make head againſt ſo great a power of the Confederates, perceiuing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that his taking of armes in ſuch hoſtile manner had greatly incenſed them againſt him, one morning very early with ſome few of his truſtieſt followers he eſcaped and fledde.</p>
            <p>Shortly after, the houſe was aſſaulted, and that which in the firſt furie was not ſpoiled and conſumed, was taken by Inuentory, and carefully preſerued. Meane while the other Comminalties of the Three Confederations deputed their chiefe officers in <hi>Agnadina,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:11"/>
who in their Aſſembly reſolued to ſend them an Embaſſage of certaine graue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons both Spirituall &amp; Temporall, with offer to ioyne with them, to reforme the Right &amp; Iuſtice in the whole State, ſo that they would lay downe armes and diſmiſſe thoſe troupes. But receiuing anſwere, that the power and Adherents of the offenders was ſo great, as that without more aſſiſtance it was vnpoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to effect what they had propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, they gaue them good acceptance, &amp; all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalties of the Countrey laid downe their Enſignes, &amp; vnited themſelues vnto them. Firſt in <hi>Coira,</hi> and then in <hi>Toſana,</hi> a village in the <hi>Griſon</hi> Confederation; where, in the Common Councell for the reeſtabliſhing of our State and gouernment, they haue reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued certaine ancient and laudable Prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Lawes, and made other new, vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of theſe late tranſgreſſions (but with all good temper and moderation) whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they alſo that ſtaide at home, haue giuen their free conſent: the ſubſtance whereof is as followeth.</p>
            <p>That both the Religions, Reformed &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, in all our Countreys and Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:3617:11"/>
ſhall haue their free exerciſe, and euery Countrey be iointly defended by all the reſt in the Religion it profeſſeth.</p>
            <p>That in all our Countreys euery Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Comminaltie, Iuriſdiction, Perſons priuate, Nobles, and common People, ſhall be maintained in their Priuiledges, Liberties, Cuſtomes, Honours, and goods, and ſhall be content in euery controuerſie and ſuite of Law with one indifferent and vnpaſſionate Iudgement.</p>
            <p>That our ſubiects ſhall be gouerned with Equitie and Iuſtice, &amp; not fall into the lawes of rauening Wolues, as heretofore diuers times hath hapned.</p>
            <p>That the Exchequer of euery ſeueral Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaltie be from henceforth more faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly looked vnto then formerly, and that it be not permitted to priuate men, to embezell and exhauſt the Publike Treaſure.</p>
            <p>That no priuate perſon preſume hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward, to treat with Princes and forraine States in matters of publike affaire, without eſpeciall commandement, vnder paine of Death: but yet, that all Leagues and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences formerly made by order of our
<pb facs="tcp:3617:12"/>
Law, ſhall be faithfully and really obſerued.</p>
            <p>And that faithfull and good neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood be kept with the borderers and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vpon all our States, &amp;c. with other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities more at large.</p>
            <p>Hereupon was eſtabliſhed a Court of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, conſiſting of moſt godly, religious, and vpright men, not Partialiſts nor engaged by oath or particular gifts to any Prince or States whatſoeuer. In which Court euery Confederation hath appointed two &amp; twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Iudges, nine Inquiſitors, two Informers, one Secretarie, and two Clarkes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath hitherto alwaies appeared, that our people haue been kept in better awe and order by the authoritie of Spirituall men, it was thought ſitte that nine of the Clergy ſhould be alwaies Aſſiſtants in the Court, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be when Sentence is to bee giuen. All which Iudges are bound by ſolemne oath, to diſcouer ſuch, as contrarie to our Law would treate with them, and eſpecially to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard no corruptions, bribes, friendſhips, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, factions, adherences, &amp; the like, which might turne them from doing right: but onely to ſet before their eyes the glory of
<pb facs="tcp:3617:12"/>
God, the ſafetie of our Countrey, and the due adminiſtration of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>The People being therefore met together, diuers ſuſpected perſons were committed to priſon, and many other conſcious of their own guiltineſſe and perfidie, ſtole away and fledde the Countrey.</p>
            <p>Among the Priſoners, the chiefe was <hi>Iohn Battiſta de Prouoſti,</hi> commonly called <hi>Zam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> dwelling in the vpper <hi>Veſpranela Brega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glia,</hi> who both by the confeſſion of ſome already executed, by the teſtimony of diuers others, &amp; by his own hand-writing, vvas co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted to haue counſailed &amp; helped with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that Fort <hi>Fuentes</hi> ſhould be built vpon the confines of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> and that the foundation being laid, &amp; the Three Confederations reſoluing by armes to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worke, as a thing contrary to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord made with <hi>Millan</hi> 1531. and to their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, &amp; priuiledges, he ſtayed the people being now ready in armes, with his falſe and perfidious pretences; and meane while wrote to the State of <hi>Millan</hi> to goe on with the worke, the enemie forces being diuerted that would haue hindred the proceeding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:13"/>
That before and after this, he had many priuiledges for tranſportation from the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> and many notable ſummes of money, not onely for the cauſes aforeſaid, but alſo for perſwading the people to a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation with <hi>Millan,</hi> as a thing profitable and neceſſarie, which notwithſtanding had turned to our great preiudice and danger, not conſidering that hee had receiued from an Embaſſadour of another Prince two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred crowns by way of Denotiue, and ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty foure of annuall penſion, with promiſe to diſſwade our people from the ſaid Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; to hinder it (albeit at other times) the ſaid <hi>Zambra</hi> and other perfidious perſons haue receiued great ſummes of money of diuers Princes, vpon promiſe to worke their ends, by our Countries preiudice, and after hath moſt ſhamefully deceiued them, and perfidiouſly broken both his word and faith giuen them.</p>
            <p>But when as <hi>Zambra</hi> had obſtinately and impudently denied both his own hand-wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the confeſſion of others, and the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of diuers honourable Perſons, he was by the Court condemned to take the <hi>Strap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pata,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:13"/>
and beeing onely pulled vp without weight, at his letting down, freely confeſſed all the circumſtances aforeſaid, and that <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulphus Planta,</hi> with others now dead, had beene authours of the counſaile for the ſaid Fort <hi>Fuentes,</hi> during the time of the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Confederates in <hi>Tauas</hi> 1603. to conſtraine our people by this meanes (as he ſaid) to haſten the League with <hi>Millan,</hi> euen as themſelues pleaſed, which league the ſaid <hi>Planta</hi> hath laboured to bee concluded and confirmed. And moreouer, beſides his many Liberties and Licences for tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Commodities, hee receiued from <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> at one time foure hundred Hungars, with promiſe of a gold chaine if the practice went forwards, beſides many goodly Donatiues for all his houſe: as alſo, that he wrote to the Marquis of <hi>Como,</hi> aduertiſing him, that the powerfull reſiſtance of the Enemy (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe of our Confederates) was now diuerted, and therefore hee ſhould not faile to finiſh the Fabrike of the ſaid Fort. And laſtly, that hee reſolued to conclude the League betweene <hi>Millan</hi> and fiue Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties only, who were deceiued and abuſed
<pb facs="tcp:3617:14"/>
by him (with falſe corruptions and many faire promiſes) although none of the reſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained or accepted it, not conſidering that our common Countrey is bound by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall and interchangeable obligation, not to accept any into their League, without the knowledge and conſent of the Maior part of the Three Confederations; All this with other things hee hath confeſſed, which is needleſſe to remember.</p>
            <p>Whereupon Sentence was pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him by the Court, vpon the 22. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt paſt, that according to the Lawes hee ſhould bee beheaded and quartered by the common hangman, as a notorious Traitour to his Countrey: And that all his goods ſhould be confiſcate to the common Exchequer of the Three Confederations; ſaue onely thoſe allotted for paiment of his debts, and his wiues portion. It was further adiudged, that his houſe ſhould be demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and razed downe to the ground, and in the place thereof two Pillars ſet vp, for a perpetuall memory and deteſtation of his fact. But after Sentence giuen, great ſuite was made for him both by the Clergy and Laity,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:14"/>
that in reſpect of his yeeres beeing ſeuentie foure, and of his nine Children, and many Kinsfolke, he might onely be beheaded, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it free to the Companies of Souldiours and common people, whether to pull down his houſe or no.</p>
            <p>Anſwerable to this, &amp; much more guiltie were found the two Brothers, <hi>Rodulphus, &amp; Pompeius Planta,</hi> who to drayne the wealth from our Countrey, and draw it into their owne hands, as alſo the chiefe Magiſtracie and gouernment therof, they haue by a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partcinory infeoffed themſelues in the Lands, and intruded themſelues into the Tutelage of all our great Widowes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans. The Marriages of great perſons were wholly at their diſpoſing, by meanes wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they procured great power and adheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ruling and commanding not onely the Subiects of <hi>Valtelina,</hi> but euen the Prouinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als themſelues, at their owne pleaſure; nay, they tyrannouſly oppreſſed their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates and free neighbours, violently en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring vpon their Eſtates, vnder colour and pretext of Iuſtice, not ſparing the liues of Laytie or Clergy, and receiuing large gifts
<pb facs="tcp:3617:15"/>
of Princes and neighbour States, promiſing much, and performing little or nothing.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 18. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> a Proceſſe was framed againſt <hi>Pompeius Planta</hi> of <hi>Zernes,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Paſchale</hi> in <hi>Donleſch,</hi> who long before the Se<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence was fled his Country: for that it clearely appeared by his owne hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writings, &amp; by Letters of his Brother <hi>Rodul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> and diuers witneſſes, that the ſaid <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peius</hi> had vſurped vpon the libertie of his Country, &amp; like a falſe Traitour had had ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret practice with forraine Princes, by which the Commonwealth was brought into emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent loſſe, &amp; imminent precipitation. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, that hee had vſurped the ſupreme Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracie in his owne Lieutenancy of <hi>Forſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau,</hi> which hee procured of the Biſhop of <hi>Coira</hi> for terme of thirtie yeeres, contrarie to the Law and cuſtome of the Countrey, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king bonds of other Officers preferred by him to like places of Magiſtracie, not to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake or conclude any buſineſſe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance without his knowledge, or of his Brother. Hee hath vvith the money of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Princes, placed all ſuch in the ſupreme gouernments of their common Countrey,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:15"/>
as ſtood affected and addicted to them, and of vvhom they might ſerue themſelues in all occurrences, at their owne will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as appeares (among others) in <hi>Lucio da Monte,</hi> to vvhom he gaue at one time two thouſand Florens of forraine Princes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and helped him to diſtribute them, that by this meanes hee might the more eaſily obtaine the office of ſupreme Iudge Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall of the <hi>Griſon</hi> Confederation, without disburſing one pennie of his owne, as by his Letter to the ſaid <hi>Pompeius</hi> appeareth: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he was forced to execute his office at the beck and command of <hi>Pompeius,</hi> that euery buſineſſe might vvholly depend vpon him, might paſſe after his humour, and bee done out of his head, and not according to the ancient Liberty of our Countrey.</p>
            <p>He hath boldly coozened and abuſed ſuch Princes and forraine States as gaue him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truſt: For once he was Broker for <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Paſquale</hi> the French Embaſſadour, to receiue &amp; diſtribute ſix thouſand Crownes, to be employed, that the League wee had contracted vvith <hi>Venice,</hi> might bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by vs, before the full date
<pb facs="tcp:3617:16"/>
were expired.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof hee receiued a great preſent to his owne proper vſe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe, beſides three hundred Crownes in Donatiue, and two hundred Frankes of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall penſion, vvhich he thought too little, as appeares by a Letter of one of his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, bearing date 12 <hi>Iuly</hi> 1612. Yet contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, hee vvrites to his Brother <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> and giues him Counſell to promiſe the State of <hi>Venice,</hi> that if they vvould grant him a Collonels place vvith 500. Crownes of yeerely penſion, both in time of Warre and Peace, vvith ſome honourable preſents be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that then hee vvould ſecretly further their demaunds: and toward <hi>France, Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he vvould ſeele vp one of his eyes, (ſuch are the very expreſſe words of his Letter) vvherein he further ſignifies, that in caſe his brother vvere not ſatisfied with the command of a French company, and that their falſhood and double dealing were diſcouered, that then hee vvould fall from <hi>France,</hi> vnder colour of more vrgent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the better to palliate his falſhood, and excuſe himſelfe to neighbour Princes. In
<pb facs="tcp:3617:16"/>
which Letter alſo we find theſe very words; Monſieur Gueffier <hi>the French Embaſsadour here reſident, would willingly there were a diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and ſedition among vs, and that wee ſhould earneſtly labour</hi> Maximilian Mora <hi>the Milla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſe Secretarie, that they would refuſe vs inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and commerce with them of that State: but I thinke he doth it to ſpare his Crownes, that we might be wholly at his deuotion, &amp; bound to no body elſe: as though that paſſage were only in the power of the French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In another of his to his Brother, bearing date the 15. of <hi>April</hi> 1616. hee writes thus: That co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Leauy of Souldiers here by the <hi>Venetians,</hi> he meant to giue his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent and aſſiſtance; but with condition, that <hi>Signor Padauino</hi> ſhould performe what hee had promiſed, (that is, large Donatiues) and though his Brother held ſtill his <hi>French</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, yet he would doe his vttermoſt for the <hi>Venetians</hi> without any danger; writing alſo in theſe vvords: <hi>They cannot ſo eaſily fall vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs, we haue (God be praiſed) more Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours ſtrangers then they: as for the French, I eſteeme them leſſe and alſo worſe, for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo eaſily piece their buſineſſe with the</hi> Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:17"/>
               <hi>and theſe men euer grow vpon vs. Lord God! who knowes what will become of the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe? We muſt put it to the venture: and yet for concluſion, I am fully reſolued in ſpite of the</hi> French, <hi>to act ſomewhat for mine owne beſt aduantage.</hi> Moreouer, in the ſaid Letter wee finde theſe words: <hi>I haue been ill at eaſe theſe two daies, elſe had I aduiſed the</hi> French-man, <hi>vpon whom I will haue an eye that hee ſhall not betray vs; we ſhall not need many words, but doe that which is requiſite.</hi> And yet the better to hide his ſecret practices, he hath written to the neighbor Princes, ſuggeſting vnto them the meanes (as appeares by his Letter) how they might hinder the League the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> demanded of vs in time of their Warres, that it might take no effect: and albeit hee hath euer made faire ſhewe to the <hi>Venetian</hi> Commonwealth, yet hee hath wrought our people with mony and other meanes, to ſtop their paſſage through our Country, to ioyne in League with the <hi>Millaneſe,</hi> and to make him abſolute Maſter of all our paſſages, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the intolerable Articles of the League propounded to vs by <hi>Millan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee bound himſelfe by ſtrict Oath to the
<pb facs="tcp:3617:17"/>
Arch-Dukes Highneſſe of <hi>Inſpruch,</hi> vpon receiuing a great Lordſhip to be held in Fee of him, as appeares by that Princes Letters of the 29. of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1613. the 26. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1615. and the 15. of <hi>October</hi> 1615. to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies faithfull to his Highneſſe as his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and Vaſſall, and to ſupply him with Souldiours at his demaund, againſt all his enemies, whereſoeuer, howſoeuer, and whenſoeuer he ſhould haue occaſion. And yet on the other ſide hee greatly miſ-prized and vilified the authoritie of that Prince in a Letter of his to his Brother <hi>Rodulphus,</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date the 15. of <hi>April</hi> 1616. and counſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him againſt Iuſtice and the Prerogatiue of that Prince in <hi>Agnadina,</hi> but withall, that the buſineſſe might be cautelouſly and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly carried.</p>
            <p>Afterwards hee ſolemnely proteſted by Oath in the publike Aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly at <hi>Tauas</hi> 1617. that he was not (effectiuely) bound to any forraine Prince or State: and yet without regard of his Oath, wherby as a perſon now placed in Authoritie he ſtood bound, nor hauing reſpect to his own Honour, or repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our common Countrey, he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:3617:18"/>
to his Highneſſe whatſoeuer was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in our Councell, ſuggeſting to that Prince, that he ſhould terrifie vs with threats, in caſe wee vndertooke the Treatie of a League with <hi>Venice;</hi> and proteſting, that if we receiued any hurt thereby, the blame ſhould lye vpon none but ourſelues, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Contents of his Letter dated the 10. of <hi>May</hi> 1615. and of his anſwer from <hi>Inſpruch</hi> the 25. of the ſame moneth.</p>
            <p>He perſwaded alſo his Highneſſe, that he would earneſtly ſollicite the Three Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations Generall, both by Letter and other meanes, that the Inhabitants of <hi>Tauas</hi> who haue many priuiledges, might become his Subiects; as appeares by his Letter of they. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1614. Hee braggeth in another of his to his Brother, that hee had intercepted ſome Letters of forrain Princes addreſſed to the Confederations Generall: and becauſe his practices ſucceeded oft-times to his wiſh, his Brother and he vainely thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo powerfull, as they might doe what they liſt in their Countrey: the reaſon was, for that in all occaſions of conuenting the Three Confederations Generall together,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:18"/>
they ſtil ouerſwayed the Councels &amp; Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vvith their pluralitie of voices, great Clientele, and Adherence, &amp;c. But as the children of darkneſſe are wiſe in their gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo theſe Brothers had prouidently complotted, that in caſe their perfidious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries were diſcouered, they would then retyre themſelues into <hi>Valtelina,</hi> where their chiefeſt friends and dependants were, or elſe ſome other-where to fortifie and arme themſelues, and ſo make a Ciuill warre vpon their natiue Countrey, as <hi>Pompeius</hi> had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly threatened: who beeing aduertiſed that the Clergy would oppoſe his deſſeignes, (and eſpecially the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> League he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) he audaciouſly anſwered amongſt other his inſolent ſpeeches, <hi>Let them looke to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, leſt they runne the like fortune that</hi> Zuinglius <hi>did in the warre of</hi> Zurich.</p>
            <p>Hee therefore hauing committed theſe and many other heinous crimes, and hauing brought his Countrey into great troubles in it ſelfe, and great diſ-reputation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with other Princes, through his teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarious perfidie; after many Citations by forme of Iuſtice and Law, hee was vpon his
<pb facs="tcp:3617:19"/>
contumacie baniſhed for life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Three Confederations Generall, with a Fine and Donatiue of a thouſand Crownes to him that ſhould bring him aliue into the hands of Iuſtice; and fiue hundred Crownes out of the publike Treaſurie to him that ſhould bring in his head. And in caſe he were taken in any of our Countreys or Iuriſdictions, that without further Proceſſe hee ſhould be executed by the common Hangman, &amp; his quarters to be ſet vp vpon the high vvayes; his houſe to be razed, and two Pillars of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy ſet vp in the place; his goods confiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to the Exchequer of the Three Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations Generall, and no man vpon paine of death euer to ſpeake or treat for his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: whoſoeuer ſhould lodge him, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit a thouſand Crownes, and to be baniſhed (as he is) for life: and if any of our Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties ſhould harbour him, to bee excluded (as perfidious) out of the Letters Patents of the Confederation.</p>
            <p>Vpon the 26. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> another Proceſſe was framed againſt <hi>Rod<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lphus Planta</hi> of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> Captaine of the Prouince of <hi>Val<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eli<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and criminall Iudge in <hi>Zernes</hi> aforeſaid and
<pb facs="tcp:3617:19"/>
the neighbour Comminalties; Captaine likewiſe of a Band of the Confederates for the French Kings ſeruice. Againſt this man it was prooued by ſeuerall Proceſſes, Confeſſions, Teſtimonies, Writings, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials of his own and his Brothers, as alſo by Letters of other his Adherents, that hee had by many and ſtrange practices brought the whole power of the Supreme Magiſtrate of the Three Confederations into his owne hands, vſing it with much tyrannie againſt both publique and priuate perſons, and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſing as well againſt our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen, as againſt Princes and forraine States: He hath treacherouſly betrayed his Countrey through his perfidious auarice, as alſo all others that truſted him; bringing vs all into diſcredit and diſpleaſure with other States, and thereby hath beene the cauſe of many Deliberations moſt preiudiciall and pernicious vnto vs.</p>
            <p>He hath intruded into the Magiſtrats place and power after this manner: His Highnes of <hi>Inſpruch</hi> hath ſome priuiledge in choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the criminall Iudge of the lower <hi>Agna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina</hi> euery S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Georges</hi> day, with the will and
<pb facs="tcp:3617:20"/>
conſent of the common people. By this meanes and that Princes fauour, <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath beene choſen Iudge diuers yeeres together: which time being expired, hee hath ſought no renewing or confirmation by the whole Bench of Iuſtice, but hath boldly vſurped the power, as if it had beene his owne by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance or purchaſe. Moreouer, of his own mee<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Authoritie hee hath arrogated the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of ciuill or criminall cauſes, by choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe for Iudges that were for his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and he that would not be pliable to his will, and ſubmit himſelfe to <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Tyrannie, was inſtantly caſſed, and another more obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to his pleaſure choſen: whereby hee hath brought the Supreme power of the Magiſtrate to be at his deuotion and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition without any contradiction, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as farre as their whole Iuriſdiction exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
            <p>He hath alſo preferred others to places of gouernment, eſpecially ſuch as could ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance any Creature and Adherent of his to the Supreme Magiſtracie, b<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> yet with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that neither he nor they ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude any thing of importance, without his
<pb facs="tcp:3617:20"/>
aduice and counſaile; but ſhould carry the buſineſſe by his direction onely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the libertie of our common Country. According to which complot he hath taken into his protection in his Caſtle of <hi>Coira, Iohn</hi> Biſhop of that place, before he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained his Libertie or Pardon: a man who for his treacherie to his Countrey and other offences, had been baniſhed from the Three Confederations Generall, by a lawfull and vnpaſſionate iudgement of both the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: which the ſaid <hi>Planta</hi> hath done, to haue the Biſhop euer ready at his will and command for the appointing of any Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (chiefly within the precincts of <hi>Cadè:)</hi> In conſideration whereof, the ſaid Biſhop granted to <hi>Pompeius Planta</hi> the Lieutenancy of <hi>Forſtenau</hi> for thirtie yeeres: where, as chiefe in the Biſhops name, hee hath power to appoint three Burgomaſters; and ſo hath he dealt with the yong Lord of <hi>Raſiuz,</hi> and many other.</p>
            <p>He hath alſo obtained of diuers great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, that when they ſhall haue any ſuites in Law depending in their Comminalties, hee onely may haue the deciſion of their
<pb facs="tcp:3617:21"/>
controuerſies, gaining power by that means to eſtabliſh in the Office that man whom he ſhall preferre: and theſe few yeeres laſt paſt, ſome Gentlemen of good qualitie in the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Agnadina,</hi> deſirous to enioy their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and cuſtome of free Election, he vvith his falſe and wicked practices ſo handled the matter, as none but his owne Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents were choſen to any Offices: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the diſpoſition of other Charges alſo, to infringe the ſtrength of pluralitie of voices, he hath beene the cauſe of ſixe mens death, beſides the endangering of many Iudges liues by force of Armes.</p>
            <p>And knowing that Monſieur <hi>Paſquale</hi> was at that time in great credit and power with vs, he ſecretly contracted with him, as appeares by a Letter of his Brother, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of one of his Adherents, bearing date the 22. of <hi>February</hi> 1611. and the 11. of <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> 1612. and by a Letter of <hi>Monſiour Paſquales</hi> owne hand: vvhich Letter ſtood <hi>Planta</hi> in good ſteade, and ſerued fitly his purpoſe; for hauing got ſtrict Intelligence vvith the Embaſſadour, euery one that deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a Penſion, vvas forced to receiue it
<pb facs="tcp:3617:21"/>
through <hi>Planta's</hi> hands; by vvhich meanes he got of the Embaſſadour large ſummes of money, new penſions, and augmentation of the old, as ſhall more amply be related in the ſumming vp of his practices.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, he hath much increaſed his Authoritie by meanes of Marriages; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in great reputation and power with his kindred and Adherents, they ranne all to him in buſineſſe of greateſt importance: &amp; if they bound themſelues to ſtand whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his direction, they got what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, elſe not.</p>
            <p>He hath alwaies kept Spies and Informers both at home and abroad, to vnderſtand the deliberations of thoſe hee ſuſpected: and finding them vpon information contrarie to his deſeignes, hee vvould firſt ſeeke to winne them; if not, he would proſecute and purſue them to their vttermoſt ruine. And to make himſelfe yet more powerful, he would falſifie and corrupt the Statutes and Lawes of the Countrey within his Iuriſdiction, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging or reſtraining them to his beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage.</p>
            <p>With theſe and the like ſleights theſe
<pb facs="tcp:3617:22"/>
thirtie fiue yeeres together, hee is growne ſo great, as for a long time hee hath engroſſed into his hands all the important buſineſſe of our Subiects, whom hee hath bound to him by diuers preſents and bribes, to elect his creatures &amp; Dependents into the Offices of ſeuerall Comminalties: by whom hee might after ſerue his owne turne to infringe the Lawes, to ſtirre vp tumults againſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, and to gouerne all at his owne pleaſure; vſing this his power with much ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie againſt all ſorts of people both Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Temporall.</p>
            <p>Hee hath moſt inſolently vſurped vpon the Iuriſdictions of the Comminalties, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuing them of their Liberties, and forcing them to depend wholly at his deuotion in the choiſe of their Magiſtrates, not daring to ſpeake or aduiſe any thing againſt him, for feare of loſing his fauour; but they all ranne as he would haue them.</p>
            <p>He hath too rigorouſly condemned poore men of the Countrey for very ſmall faults, and then compounded with them for no ſmall gifts and bribes, without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or conſent of the Court: wherevnto
<pb facs="tcp:3617:22"/>
the poore men were enforced to auoid his tyrannous perſecution, and were bound by Oath not to complaine or once ſpeake of the wrong he had done them: whereof we haue here ſet downe ſome few particulars among many hundreds; and theſe they be:</p>
            <p>A man beeing fledde vpon a certaine cryme committed, and dead in the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines; <hi>Planta</hi> forceth the poore heyres of the dead man to pay two hundred and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Florens for his eſcape: contrary to the Lawes of the Countrey, which condemne a man only in ten Florens for his flight: which Fine is alſo to be payed to the whole Court, not to the criminall Iudge alone.</p>
            <p>If at any time an offender endited and conuicted, had accuſed another of ſome ſmall crime, he would not diſcouer the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, nor call the partie in queſtion, till af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the execution of the Accuſer: And though the partie accuſed knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he vvere indeed charged by that other, or that it vvas a thing of <hi>Planta's</hi> owne for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and much complained that hee vvas not called to his anſwere vvhile the Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer liued: yet was hee forced to compound
<pb facs="tcp:3617:23"/>
vvith him for round ſummes of Money, to auoid his indignation, and vniuſt perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Two men confeſſed vpon the Torture, that they had ſtolne a certaine quantitie of Wheate from a neighbour of theirs: the man hearing of their confeſſion, ſaid hee knew of none he had loſt: for vvhich word alone, <hi>Planta</hi> fined him ſecretly at fortie Crownes, threatning, that if he paid not the money, he would caſt him in priſon, and put him to Torture, to confeſſe whether he loſt any wheate or no.</p>
            <p>Vpon a time he ſending his Warrant for one accuſed, to appeare before him at <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> he demanded a horſe of a woman for that ſeruice, to ſend him backe to priſon, whoſe Husband vvas gone to the wood with him: <hi>Planta</hi> ſeemes offended that the horſe could not bee had: the poore Wife ſends preſently to her Husband, to make vvhat haſte he could with his Horſe from the wood: the good-man, though he came home preſently after the Iudge and the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner vvere departed, and made haſte after them to offer them his Horſe, he had anſwer,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:23"/>
that now they had got another to ſerue their turne: all this notwithſtanding, <hi>Planta</hi> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the poore man in fiue and twentie Crownes, becauſe hee had not offered his Horſe before he vvent to the wood.</p>
            <p>Two men being in ſuite for a matter not aboue halfe a Crowne, one gaue in eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: <hi>Planta</hi> preſently laid to his charge that he had giuen falſe vvitneſſe; threatning him the Torture, and that he would plucke out his tongue by the rootes. Hereat the poore man was ſo much affrighted, as hee promiſed <hi>Planta</hi> a ſecret Donatiue of two hundred Crownes to bee leauied vpon his Lands, and was afterward forced to diſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage them of that morgage with a hundred and twenty Hungars, beſides threeſcore Crownes Fine for the accuſation, and fifty more for charges of the Court.</p>
            <p>Foure free men of the Confederation, bringing from <hi>Chiauenna</hi> into <hi>Finſcouia</hi> ſome loades of Rice vpon their own horſes, and paſſing through the lower <hi>Agnadina,</hi> bartring their Rice for Wheat, they returned with their ſaid loading and Merchandize through <hi>Zernes: Planta</hi> preſently charged
<pb facs="tcp:3617:24"/>
them by his cruell practice to make their market, and vent their commoditie in the vpper <hi>Agnadina,</hi> or elſe they ſhould bee fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for vſing their owne horſes, and not thoſe of his neighbours: who refuſing to ſatisfie him herein, they were fined at a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Florens.</p>
            <p>One ſaid to a neighbour of his, that if hee had paid <hi>Planta</hi> the money hee ought him, he would not owe him the putting off of his cap: he was for theſe words onely, fined in an hundred Crownes.</p>
            <p>He plotted that ſtrange ſtratageme in the vpper <hi>Agnadina,</hi> where he incenſed two ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane brothers one againſt the other: and that ſide which hee abbetted hauing the vvorſe, he ſent to his aide two hundred and fiftie men, to obtaine that by vnlawfull waies and open violence, which hee could not compaſſe by corruptions, promiſes, and menaces: By which tumult hee was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of ſix honourable mens death, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many other ſore wounded.</p>
            <p>Hee hath alſo beene an Aſſaſſinate and bloud-ſucker of the Clergie: for a Prieſt of <hi>Monſtertall</hi> ſeeing his perfidious practices,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:24"/>
and ſpeaking ſomewhat freely of them, hee ſo perſecuted the man vvith his calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as at length he cauſed him to dye by the hand of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, they of the reformed Clergie oppoſing the Capitulations of the League propounded betweene our Confederations and the houſe of <hi>Millan,</hi> in the yeere 1617. and publiquely reprouing diuers other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, ſome of them hee perſecuted vvith his criminall Authoritie; others he laboured to remooue from their Miniſterie; ſome hee violently ſet vpon in his owne perſon; ſome he impriſoned and threatned to doe worſe vnto them; vpon others his ſeruants bent their Piſtols, and Harquebuſies charged, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing to kill them: Hee hath fined diuers men for ſpeaking well of their Doctors and Miniſters. Finally, the perfidie and falſhood of his notorious practices is vnſpeakeable: for many times hee takes bribes to the ſumme of a thouſand Florens and more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene both parties in difference, and in the end ſhamefully deceiues the one and the other.</p>
            <p>To defend a Traitour and ſaue him
<pb facs="tcp:3617:25"/>
harmeleſſe from danger of the Law, hee tooke a bribe of a thouſand and fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Crownes. In another caſe of difference, he tooke ſeuen hundred &amp; eightie Crownes of one partie, and a thouſand of the other, and then failed them both. In a difference of ſuite depending betweene two Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, hee tooke foure hundred Crownes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece, and effected nothing for either.</p>
            <p>His treacherous practices againſt his Countrey cannot ſufficiently be related, as appeareth by vvhat hath beene ſaid, and by his indeuours at all times to make himſelfe Lord of the Gouernment: as likewiſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the Proceſſe of <hi>Zambra,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actions of his owne, vvhich tended to fauour and further the treacherous capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vvith the houſe of <hi>Millan,</hi> to depriue vs of our Priuiledges and Iuriſdictions, and to enthrall vs vnder the power of forraine Princes. Among other meanes he hath vſed, hee hath alſo ſerued his turne of theſe which follow:</p>
            <p>The yeare 1603. he complotted with <hi>Iohn Battiſta Zambra,</hi> to further or rather enforce a League aboue and againſt all other intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences
<pb facs="tcp:3617:25"/>
and Leagues wee had formerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, labouring that the Fort <hi>Fuentes</hi> might be built, and withholding our people from hindring the proceeding of the ſaid vvorke. And the Three Confederations Generall in the yeere 1606. being truely en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that all their ſecrets of State vvere diſcouered to forraine Princes, they eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed a Priuy Councell of fifteene men, to the intent that all their Deliberations might bee entruſted to ſecret Confidence: whereupon <hi>Planta</hi> and his Complices being ſo debarred from the knowledge of any thing, raiſed that dangerous tumult in the yeere 1607.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn-Peter Mora da Piur,</hi> hath alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed <hi>Planta's</hi> Treaſon touching the Fort, and that he was moued by him and wonne by his ſubtill ſleights, corruptions, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiues, to the calling back of his forces, as by <hi>Planta's</hi> Letter to his Brother <hi>Pompeius</hi> appeareth, and by Letters of other his Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents dated the 3. of <hi>October</hi> 1604.</p>
            <p>In the yeere 1610. to our great loſſe and griefe, the French King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth was murthered, after whoſe death, <hi>Monſieur Paſquale</hi> the French Embaſſadour reſident
<pb facs="tcp:3617:26"/>
with vs, ſent a ſecret diſpatch to <hi>Millan</hi> in the yeere 1611. to treat with <hi>Signor Alphonſo Caſale,</hi> Embaſſadour in <hi>Switzerland</hi> for the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> that he would cauſe a League or new intelligence to be made between the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> and the Three Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Generall: and to the intent the ſaid Treatie might not bee hindred, the ſaid <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour and Captaine <hi>Planta</hi> beeing both agreed vpon the buſineſſe (though the <hi>French</hi> Kings were alwaies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it) hee gaue <hi>Planta</hi> ſixe thouſand Crownes of gold, and two thouſand and fiue hundred Frankes of yeerely penſion, to be diſtributed as he thought good, without being bound to make any account, that hee and his Adherents would help to breake the League with <hi>Venice,</hi> which was contrarie to the Treatie betweene <hi>Millan</hi> and vs: as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the Letters of <hi>Pompeius</hi> and his Adherents in the yeere 1612. and by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall written with Captaine <hi>Planta's</hi> own hand.</p>
            <p>The renunciation of the League between the State of <hi>Venice</hi> and vs beeing procured and bought by money, <hi>Planta</hi> preſently
<pb facs="tcp:3617:26"/>
drawes out ſome Articles of the League of <hi>Zuz:</hi> Wherein ſome Comminalties dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vpon the Paſſages, are bound not to grant paſſage to any whatſoeuer through our Countries, that all friendſhip and aide of ours towards the <hi>Venetians</hi> might be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. And the ſaid <hi>Caſale</hi> hauing in the yeere 1617. required a League with vs, and free paſſage, in name of the houſe of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> they which were authors of the League of <hi>Zuz,</hi> and of the deniall of paſſage to the Souldiers of forraine States, were the firſt that granted the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> free paſſage for his Forces, through all our Countreys and vpon all occaſions, contrary to what they had formerly concluded: So that the falſhood of <hi>Planta</hi> and his Adherents dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appeared.</p>
            <p>Againſt theſe Treaties of <hi>Planta</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Complices, diuers good Patriots both of the Clergie and Laitie ſo earneſtly laboured, as they were by no meanes accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: herevpon <hi>Planta</hi> much enraged, thought vpon a ſpeedy and liuely reuenge, beginning to proſecute thoſe of moſt honeſtie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, farre more then formerly hee had
<pb facs="tcp:3617:27"/>
done, and ſtirring them of the vpper <hi>Agna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina</hi> to tumult, hee made them riſe in Armes with Enſignes diſplayed, to thruſt violently <hi>Signor Padauino</hi> out of our Countrey, vvho had retyred himſelfe before their comming: he hath alſo conuented the people together, brought thither by his Adherents and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, framing diuers barbarous Articles, and conſtraining all men to obſerue them.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of which Articles was this: That no Church-man of any Comminaltie ſhould dare to ſpeake or giue his voice in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buſineſſe concerning the Countrey: though this be lawfull to euery free man of our State, be he neuer ſo poore and baſe: and this he did, becauſe in all his machinations and plots, hee neuer found ſtiffer reſiſtance then from the Clergie. Moreouer, they haue had diuers and ſundry conſultations vvith <hi>Maximilian Mora</hi> to put them to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and ſtop their mouthes altogether: and laſtly, they haue found it fit to forbid them by a generall Law, not to meddle with matters of State, or the good of their common Countrey, or to bee informers of the preſent corruptions. So much the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell
<pb facs="tcp:3617:27"/>
hath blinded their eyes, that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can, nor vvill ſee or ſuffer the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome admonition of faithfull Subiects.</p>
            <p>They haue alſo ſettled a Court of Iuſtice, the decrees whereof (by confeſſion of ſome of the Iudges themſelues) were wholly ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and diſpatched by the aduice and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the two Brothers onely. Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges alſo were choſen, ſuch as ſtood partially affected to forraine Princes, of whoſe libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie they had bountifully taſted: who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were bound by Oath to defend the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Coira,</hi> againſt our Prouinciall lawes, to which they were ſworne: vvhich they did by many indirect waies, and by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement of the inwardeſt friends to the <hi>Planta's,</hi> who by their bad proceedings haue deceiued many honeſt men, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers honourable Comminalties, with their large ſummes of money.</p>
            <p>More eſpecially, they haue perſecuted the ſaid Clergie, calling them to appeare before them, and charging them not to meddle, or once ſpeake in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> buſineſſe, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſome of them in groſſe ſummes for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpoken too much: and among the reſt,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:28"/>
they brought one Preacher by force from his houſe in <hi>Coira,</hi> without any cauſe but meere malice; threatening impriſonment, and death, or baniſhment to others.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, they haue offered to maintaine the Biſhop of <hi>Coira</hi> with ſtrong hand: who (as is aforeſaid) had beene baniſhed by Proclamation out of the Three Confederations Generall, and hath lately beene charged by forme of Law with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notorious crimes: and not regarding his manifold tranſgreſſions, they haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to his eſcape out of the Countrey, and granted free paſſage for his goods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</p>
            <p>Theſe tumults <hi>Planta</hi> hath not onely cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as is manifeſt by many vvitneſſes <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua voce,</hi> but he hath alſo granted tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Commodities, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the State, in a time when the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were ſhut, and commerce forbidden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene vs and <hi>Millan:</hi> though at the ſame time his Brother <hi>Pompeius</hi> wrote to him, that <hi>Monſieur Gueffier</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour had importuned <hi>Maximilian Mora,</hi> to deſire the ſtopping of the paſſage and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:28"/>
alledging, that he deſired a commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſedition among vs.</p>
            <p>And now this preſent yeere 1618. ſome of our Comminalties riſing in Armes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy this miſchiefe, hee preſently bound by Oath the men of his Circuit to demand aide of others, thereby to mooue a Ciuill warre, that the common people butchering one another, he might ſubdue the ſtronger part remaining, and ſo make himſelfe vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall and abſolute Lord of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey. But foreſeeing that this plot vvould faile him, and doubting that hee ſhould be cited to anſwere the Law for his notorious miſ-demeanours, he preſently fled: vpon his flight, he was according to cuſtome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times ſummoned, and neuer appeared. Seeing therefore he hath vſurped the chiefe Authoritie of our Countrey, as to giue and aboliſh Lawes, to make and renounce Leagues, to create and depoſe Magiſtrates, to diſpoſe of Warre and Peace, and hath vſed this his power with all manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidie, deceit, violence, tyrannie, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; he hath beene by the Law and Iuſtice of our Countrey, condemned to perpetuall
<pb facs="tcp:3617:29"/>
baniſhment from all the Three Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Generall, and left free to the Birds of the ayre: with a reward and Fee of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes to him ſhall bring him aliue into our Countrey, and to him ſhall bring in his head fiue hundred Crownes; beſides his freeing from the Proclamation, if hee ſtand baniſhed for any other offence, but Treaſon againſt the State, or wilfull mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: which money ſhall be paid out of the Common Treaſury: And in caſe he be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in our Country, or yeeld himſelfe into the hands of the Three Confederations Generall, that then the Magiſtrate ſhall call a Court of Iuſtice of the Three Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and without any farther Proceſſe ſhall order, that he be forthwith executed and quartered by the common Hangman, and his quarters to be ſet vp in the common high waies: all his goods to be confiſcate to the Chamber of the common Treaſurie, ſauing the dowrie of his wife, and the paiment of his cleere debts; his houſe to be razed, and two pillars ſet vp in the place, to his perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all infamy: and that Comminaltie which ſhall refuſe to execute this Sentence, and
<pb facs="tcp:3617:29"/>
ſhall ſuccour him with meate, drinke or lodging, ſhall forfeit their Right in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation, and beſides, for euery ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall be fined in a thouſand Crownes: and if he be a priuate perſon, he ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of his honours, and forfeit a thouſand Crownes: but he that is not worth ſo much in goods or lands, ſhall forfeit his life: and laſtly, if any ſpeake of his Pardon, write to him, or talke with him, or ſhall receiue or reade his Letters, ſhall likewiſe loſe his life.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Interim,</hi> vpon the 22. of <hi>Auguſt, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colo Ruſca da Lugano,</hi> Arch-prieſt of <hi>Sondrio</hi> in <hi>Valtelina,</hi> was accuſed, who formerly had beene impriſoned by the People, for hauing conſpired with <hi>Iohn-Paolo Quadrio</hi> of <hi>Ponte, &amp; Vince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>zo Gatto</hi> of <hi>Coira,</hi> to kil <hi>Signor Scipio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Calandrino</hi> late Preacher in <hi>Sondrio,</hi> in caſe they could finde him vpon the State of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> or elſe to carry him out of our State, to <hi>Millan</hi> or to <hi>Rome,</hi> as diuers times hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it had happened to others; as <hi>Michael Ciappino</hi> hath publiquely confeſſed, both vpon the Torture and after: who being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to act this his bloudy purpoſe, <hi>Calan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drino</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:30"/>
had notice by ſome of his friends, that the Arch-prieſt lay in waite for his life, and had his Spies vpon him: as appeared by a Briefe of his ſent to <hi>Ciappino</hi> by a yong Lad; wherin he giues him aduertiſement, when, and in what place he might come with his complices, and in what manner hee might performe that felonious act: where vpon <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appino</hi> was impriſoned in the yeere 1698. in the moneth of <hi>September,</hi> vnder the charge of Captaine <hi>Iohn Corn</hi> of <hi>Caſtelmur:</hi> where, vpon proofe of the Euidence, hee ſuffered death, as appeares by his Proceſſe and the confeſſions vnder the hand and ſeale of the ſaid <hi>Signor Capitan<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Ciappino</hi> had to this purpoſe made choiſe of certaine Ferry-men, <hi>Andrea Serem da Como, Iohn Pifer the Traona,</hi> and <hi>Battista Domini da Menus,</hi> who in the yeere 1594. <hi>Iuly,</hi> were all executed, becauſe being at the Ferry-place of the Riuer <hi>Adde,</hi> where <hi>Calandrino</hi> was retyred, they would violently haue haled him into their Barque; but they were apprehended by <hi>Signor Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tano Artman de Artmani,</hi> and the whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being proued againſt them, they were for the ſaid murtherous conſpiracie and
<pb facs="tcp:3617:30"/>
treaſonable plot condemned to die.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, this <hi>Ruſca</hi> had ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a Rebel and diſobedient to the ſupreme Magiſtrate of the Three Confederations Generall, becauſe hee embezeled and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Decrees and Records of that Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: and afterwards holding his Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Cloiſters at <hi>Sondrio,</hi> there were heard many ſeditious and rebellious words by diuers honeſt men in the ſtreets, which they haue fully teſtified and proued, and as ſince hath beene confirmed by <hi>Nicolo Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonera,</hi> both vpon and after Torture: affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming moreouer, that hee had giuen coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile to cancell ſome Decrees of his owne State, by the procurement of the <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadours, in whom <hi>Signor Iulio della Torre</hi> had great intereſt to preuaile, as a faithfull and truſtie friend of theirs: That he had alſo hindred the free courſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>He had ſo farre made himſelfe Maſter of the peoples will, that the Officers of <hi>Valteli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> fearing ſome ſodaine tumult &amp; inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, durſt not lay open his horrible crimes and tranſgreſſions. In the time while Fort
<pb facs="tcp:3617:31"/>
               <hi>Fuentes</hi> was building, he retyred to <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begno,</hi> where, (as is prooued by diuers Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies &amp; his own confeſſion) he perſwaded the people, not to make warre with ſo Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique a Prince as the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> but to keepe their conſciences free, and to aske him pardon for their fault: reſiſting by that meanes the Proueditor of the Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Generall, who was forced patiently to diſſemble this rebellious affront: and albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he was reſolued to charge him herewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all before the Councellors and Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet he deferred it till the fourth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1608. at what time hee was ſummoned before the Comminalties, and in <hi>Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> after, before the Iuſtice Court of the Three Confederations Generall of both the Religions; but being conſcious of his own guiltineſſe, he neuer appeared.</p>
            <p>He hath alſo by aſſiſtance of his Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces laboured to corrupt and drawe many men to his partie, as appeares by Letters of his written to a friend the 22, 23, and 24. of <hi>December</hi> the ſame yeere, as alſo by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of diuers honeſt men; wherevpon euen they that were corrupted by him, haue
<pb facs="tcp:3617:31"/>
receiued condigne puniſhment, but yet with clemencie.</p>
            <p>He hath held particular correſpondencie and ſecret conference with the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of forraine Princes, and eſpecially hee hath had ſtrict intelligence and practice with the diſloyall Rebels of our Countrey, fauouring many of their pernicious deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeignes, as appeares by writings of his own and others: nay, during the time of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing paſſage and commerce with the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> he made a iourney twice to that Citie, not without our great ſuſpition and iealouſie. Which ſaid accuſations com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming before the Court of Iuſtice, and the Iudges calling into ſerious conſideration our ancient Lawes and proceedings, and carefully peruſing and examining the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Letters, as alſo thoſe written by <hi>Paolo da Sulmona</hi> Prieſt, the 6. of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1608. by <hi>Signor Philippo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Como</hi> the 15. of <hi>March</hi> 1610. and by Fryer <hi>Francis</hi> Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall of his order in <hi>Millan,</hi> bearing date the 12. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1611. and by many other Letters addreſſed to him, and by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of honeſt men heard and approued,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:32"/>
they all appeare to the Court to be true and iuſtifiable.</p>
            <p>This man notwithſtanding gaineſayed all, denied the confeſſions of thoſe had beene tortured and executed, made a ridiculous ſcoffe of the Letters and atteſtations, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to excuſe himſelfe and put off the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with a ieſt: but withall he beſought the Court they would proceede no farther a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but either ſend him to perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all baniſhment, or condemne him to the Gallies. Herevpon they adiudged him to bee tortured: the firſt day hee was hoiſed thrice without any weight; nor would hee confeſſe any thing: the ſecond day being twice drawne vp by the Pulley, he ſeemed very feeble; vpon this they let him downe to the ground, and looſned his cords, when inſtantly he dyed, not without ſtrong ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that he had poiſoned himſelfe, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the tokens in his body. So by the Sentence of Iuſtice hee was carried by the Hangman to the publike place of executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and there buried.</p>
            <p>A rumour was ſpred abroad by ſome falſe Calumniators, that this <hi>Ruſca</hi> was tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured
<pb facs="tcp:3617:32"/>
to death in priſon, by the malice of thoſe of the Religion: but worthy men of both the Religions that were then and there preſent, can witneſſe the contrarie: becauſe, during the two daies wherein he was tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he was not in all aboue one houre on the Torture: beſides, his torture was moſt eaſie, but his death came by ſome other meanes, as hath beene declared.</p>
            <p>The firſt day of <hi>September, Iohn-Antonio Giouer da Calanca</hi> was called in queſtion, whoſe owne Letter, and others, with their Proceſſe and witneſſes doe teſtifie, that he had plotted to bring a warre vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and to this end had ſought to raiſe For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in forraine States.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn-Battiſta Zambra,</hi> of whom we haue formerly made mention, hath confeſſed, that <hi>Giouer</hi> had not onely conueyed his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and directions to <hi>Millan,</hi> but alſo that hauing written to him to be ready at the ſeruice of the houſe of <hi>Millan,</hi> and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Leauy of the Three Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the building of Fort <hi>Fuentes,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Giouer</hi> had returned him this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere; That he would aduance the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3617:33"/>
as much as hee could.</p>
            <p>He hath by his Letters and Spies diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the ſecret Counſailes of the Three Confederations Generall to forraine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, making offer to procure a good iſſue to their affaires, rather then to thoſe of his owne Countrey. By his counſaile the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Millan</hi> was ſhut vp, ſo was it by vs to them of that State: yet he by his Office ſuffered many horſes and other things to paſſe from this State thither, and hath crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wrought that the Salt and Graine of that State might be kept from hence: hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſecretly diſtributed money here, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt others againſt the Priuiledges of our higher Powers.</p>
            <p>He hath, contrarie to the Liberty of our Religion and publique Peace, ſtirred vp cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Comminalties of the Three Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations Generall, one againſt another by lies and falſe reports: and namely, he counſailed and helped to burne the Seates of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in the Church of <hi>Maſo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> their Bels to bury vnder ground, and driue out the Miniſters; wherein himſelfe was a princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Actor, and for which worthy ſeruice he
<pb facs="tcp:3617:33"/>
was Knighted by the Pope, to whom hee tooke his Oath, contrary to the Allegeance he owes to his owne Countrey.</p>
            <p>Hee publiſhed a counterfeit Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at <hi>Morbegno,</hi> in the name of the Three Confederations Generall, That thoſe who goe to <hi>Venice,</hi> ſhould not onely be denied en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment and lodging, but alſo hee that ſhould kill any of them, ſhould be free from all danger of puniſhment or Fine. Many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notorious outrages he hath committed, not needfull here to be related. Being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore two ſeuerall times ſummoned to the Court of Iuſtice, and not appearing, he was baniſhed, and had like Sentence of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation with that of Captaine <hi>Rodulphus Planta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day Proceſſe was framed by due courſe of Iuſtice againſt <hi>Lucio di Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> chiefe Iudge of the <hi>Griſon</hi> Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for that it was euidently prooued by his owne Letters, and others, and by diuers wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that he made his way to that Office by the money of forreine Princes, aſſiſting them and their affaires in matter of State, with all his power; receiuing at one time
<pb facs="tcp:3617:34"/>
two hundred Doubles of <hi>Spaine</hi> from a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretarie to a forreine Prince, and from an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Prince three hundred gold Crownes for the like ſeruice. Hee hath likewiſe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much money from a certaine Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of a forraine Prince, and disburſed ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hundred Crownes for obtaining the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Lantama,</hi> or chiefe Iuſtice of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gniz</hi> with corruption and preſents: and yet (to the terrour of all men) tooke his corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Oath, that he entertained no ſecret prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice with any forraine State.</p>
            <p>While hee was in his office of ſupreme Iudge and <hi>Lantama,</hi> he countenanced and furthered the ſeditious tumult of 1617. whereby many good men were perſecuted, the Confederation of <hi>Cadè</hi> brought into great expenſes, and the Three Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Generall into extreme danger. He hath further threatened when State matters were in handling, that vnleſſe they ſucceeded as he would haue them, he would cauſe to be made ſuch a hauock and ſpoile among them, as it ſhould reach to their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and loſſe of life. He ſhewed his readineſſe to receiue 50000. Crownes, for ſolliciting
<pb facs="tcp:3617:34"/>
the vniuſt Articles of the League with <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> and working vs to a conſent thereunto: wherein notwithſtanding, the reſt of his Complices would not giue their conſent, for feare, if the League ſhould goe forward, he would keepe all the money to himſelfe. Moreouer, hee hath held ſtrict practices with forrenners, to the great preiudice of our State, and hath dared to bragge that he had ſeuenteene of our Comminalties within the League of <hi>Cadè,</hi> at his command, and in the reſt of our Confederations he was growne ſo powerfull and ſtrong, as he nothing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed the contrarie partie: whereby hee became ſo inſolent, as he would force them to his ends by open violence, or elſe threaten to kill them like Calues. Laſtly, he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Armes, with ſuccours of forraine States againſt his owne Countrey.</p>
            <p>Hereof being conſcious, and of many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther villanies, he is fled the Countrey and Liberties thereof: and being ſummoned by the Court of Iuſtice, and not making appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, he was baniſhed, and receiued like Sentence of condemnation with <hi>Pompeius Planta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:35"/>
Some few daies after, <hi>Iohn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> was accuſed, who eleuen yeeres ſince had beene baniſhed by order of Law, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall iudgement of both the Religions of the Three Confederations Generall, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny foule crimes, and other tranſgreſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Countrey: namely, for aduiſing and aſſiſting that the Three Confederations Generall might not keepe their Oath and couenant (which they ought) with other Princes and forrain States their Colleagues: and for receiuing and disburſing diuers ſummes of money, that wee might oppoſe the Lords of <hi>Switzerland</hi> our faithfull Neighbours and Confederates. Likewiſe, he put his Biſhopricke vnder the Protection of thoſe that were our profeſſed and ſworne enemies, and knowing himſelfe guilty of this perfidie, he laboured (in caſe his vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies ſhould come to light) to hold the Office of a Legate in the Countries of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie.</p>
            <p>Not long after, contrarie to the Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Three Confederations for his baniſhment, he being confederate with the diſloyall and traiterous men of our
<pb facs="tcp:3617:35"/>
Countrey, who had then the power of the Supreme Magiſtrate in their owne hands, and returning to his Biſhopricke at <hi>Coira,</hi> whither he was brought by <hi>Rodulphus Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> chiefe head of the Treaſon againſt his Countrey, he hath here continued in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer practices, and perſiſted in his pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous complottings againſt the State. Hee hath robbed our Houſe neere <hi>Fuſtemburgh</hi> in his Dioceſſe, and hath placed therein a perfidious perſon, and one baniſhed our State.</p>
            <p>Hee hath contrarie to Law taken away the Hereditarie Lands belonging to his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, from thoſe that poſſeſſed them by deſcent, but were not of his Epiſcopall fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and giuen them to others of his owne partie. He hath aliened and conueied away diuers Lands from his Church, without the conſent or knowledge of the League of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dè,</hi> which is Viſiter and Protector of that Biſhoprick; and hath employed wicked, perfidious, and temerarious perſons, in his ſeruice, and againſt the State. He hath prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in Villages of matters of State, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to his Oath, and the dignitie of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.
<pb facs="tcp:3617:36"/>
He hath taken bribes in differences and ſuites in Law betweene party and party, concerning the Limits and boundaries of our Countrey, euer aſſiſting that ſide which oppoſed vs. He ſtileth his confederates that are of the reformed Religion, by the name of Heretiques, when he mentioneth them to forraine Princes, contrarie to the peace of our Religion and Countrey. He hath denied them buriall in that part of his Iuriſdiction which is out of our Countrey, ſo as they are forced to bring the corps hither to haue Chriſtian buriall: beſides many other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialities. And hauing had notice that his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were made knowne to the Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Councellors, he retyred himſelfe laſt yeere out of our Iuriſdiction: and being lawfully ſummoned to the Court, he failed to appeare. Herevpon the honourable Court of Iuſtice proceeded againſt him the 15. of <hi>September</hi> this preſent yeere, and vpon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient examination of his own hand-writing, and others, diuers witneſſes being produced and heard, and all the premiſſes cleerely prooued, beſides many other; the Court hath decreed to adde new vigour to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:3617:36"/>
Proclamation of his baniſhment for life; confiſcating all his own proper goods, and reſeruing thoſe of the Biſhoprick: and hath further commanded the League of <hi>Cadè,</hi> and the Deane and Chapter of that Cathedrall Church, to proceed as ſpeedily as conueniently they may, to the election of a new Biſhop: ſtraightly charging and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all men to harbour him in the Countrey, and being taken there, to haue his head cut off.</p>
            <p>Proceſſe was likewiſe framed againſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, whoſe ſeuerall crimes &amp; offences for breuities ſake we omit. But beſides the former, wee finde other wicked men ſo much corrupted and bribed with Preſents and Donatiues from the Miniſters of the French King, as they haue not onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to obſerue the League, (in which caſe no bribes were needfull, euery man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſolued to keepe his Oath and beare himſelfe as became his honour and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) but alſo to apply themſelues in all things to the good will and pleaſure of thoſe publike Miniſters: and accordingly, ſome ſeruants of his ſaid Maieſty haue
<pb facs="tcp:3617:37"/>
thruſt themſelues into buſineſſes not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in the Articles, promiſing not to giue paſſage through our Countreys, (as if they were their owne) and not to giue their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that we ſhould enter League with any other.</p>
            <p>Theſe very men, vpon acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great Donatiues and expectation of greater ſummes promiſed, haue likewiſe made themſelues Vaſſals and humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to the Catholique Kings Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> he hoping by this meanes to obtaine his demand in our Countrey; namely, that the King his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter may be abſolute Lord of all our paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. And yet theſe ſelfe-ſame men haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken money of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> to further their demand of ſome Troupes of ours, or elſe to haue free paſſage for thoſe they ſhould lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy from other places; or at leaſt if any ſhould fauour their affaire, to be ſilent, and heare and ſee nothing. By which meanes, drawing to themſelues the treaſures of other Princes, and impudently coozening both the one ſide and other, they haue brought our common Countrey into diſcredit and
<pb facs="tcp:3617:37"/>
diſ-reputation: hence it is, that many of them who had but a ſmall patrimony left them by their Anceſtors, come now to liue ſplendidly, and grow infinitely rich.</p>
            <p>Some of theſe men haue beene baniſhed their Countrey, and had they beene taken, they had beene ſentenced to be hanged and beheaded: ſome haue forfeited their eſtates, honours, and Armes; others put out of our Councels; others haue loſt their money and goods; and many haue beene accuſed that haue cleered themſelues; who not beeing conuicted of any crime, either by their own writing, confeſſion, or teſtimonie of honeſt and Legall men, they haue beene diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged without paying one penny of mulct, or Fees of the Court whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>So that in concluſion, whoſoeuer vvill take knowledge of our manner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſhall euidently ſee, that we haue beene forced thereunto by vrgent neceſſity. Firſt, that God the Lord of Hoſts might be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, who hath planted vs in this Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall and Ciuill Liberty; and ſecondly, that our common Countrey might be preſerued by Iuſtice, to the extermination and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:3617:38"/>
of all Treaſons, the puniſhment of all notorious offences, the aduancement of true vertue and loyall honeſty, the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of euill abuſes, and reſtauration of our ancient Liberty, for the ſincere and reall propagation thereof to our Poſteritie.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the true cauſes and reaſons why we are falſely ſlandered and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niated by our perfidious Countreymen and other malicious perſons, blaming vs to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princes and forraine States, as if this our Aſſembly and Iudiciall proceeding had been onely appointed for priuate factions, wicked emulations, hatred againſt the Romane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion, and deſpight of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates &amp; ancient friends, to change them for new, &amp; colleague our ſelues with them. But we are in good hope, that they who ſhall heare ſuch perſons talke, againſt whom we haue ſent out our Proceſſe and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, will likewiſe remember, that they are the ſame men who haue ſo falſely and ſo often deceiued forraine Princes and States our neighbours, receiuing great ſummes of money from them, and in word promiſing much in diuers places, but in effect perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb facs="tcp:3617:38"/>
nothing. And as they haue vainely ſought to excuſe their falſhood againſt their accuſers, ſo no doubt they will not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with falſe machinations and preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to palliate and cloke their malice.</p>
            <p>If theſe ſo powerfull men haue beene faithfull Miniſters in the gouernment of our Countrey, and haue carried themſelues with ſuch integritie and ſinceritie towards all men, why doe other Princes and States complaine of our ill gouernment, and of our dayly changing our Councels, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe men haue beene the onely occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Why doe they conteſt with Barons and Earles in all manner of riches and magnificence, and yet leaue the Countrey empty of all prouiſion? Can a Prince or forraine State complaine of any mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidie, and not of theſe, with whom he hath had ſo ſtrict intelligence, who promiſed them much, yet neither did nor could doe any thing? Who can charge vs to haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted any one Family or Comminaltie through faction or emulation, ſince it plainely appeareth, that the perſons execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted were of diuers Families and Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties?
<pb facs="tcp:3617:39"/>
who will imagine they were falſely ſlandered of diuers things, when the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles whereof they ſtood accuſed, appeared to be plainely prooued by their own hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writings, and thoſe of their Complices? Who will beleeue that their faults are ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauated, and they condemned not being guilty, when their owne writings, actions, and confeſſions do plainely giue euidence, that the bloudy Fort <hi>Fuentes</hi> was built by their counſaile, aſſiſtance, and contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? who alſo pronounced them enemies that hindred the worke, and bewrayed the ſecret deliberations of our Countrey, which were ſo honeſt, ſincere, and to no man pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall: preſcribing vs the way how to carry our ſelues in that buſineſſe, that through feare we might become baſe and puſillanimous; to which ſeruice they were drawne by money, like vile and mercenary perſons.</p>
            <p>But they ſay we haue a particular Faction by which they are perſecuted. This which they call Faction, is that which deſireth to aduance, preſerue, and defend the Honour and Word of God, conſiſting of all the reall
<pb facs="tcp:3617:39"/>
and true Subiects of our Countrey of both Religions. This is the Faction, that deſireth to keepe the Liberties of our Countrey, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our ancient lawes and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This is the Faction, that deſireth to maintaine their Faith, Honour, and Oath, with all their Confederates. This is the Faction, that now for many yeeres hath promiſed to receiue no Penſion of forraine Princes for matters of State, and that neuer made promiſe of any thing that it hath not faithfully performed; and for long time hath with much patience and more griefe endured ſuch wicked perſons. Theſe are the children and poſteritie of thoſe that haue freed themſelues from Tyrants, and will no longer acknowledge their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors as Superiours, but as neighbours; and theſe are they that ſuſtaine &amp; ſupport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues by their integritie; they hate all Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy and Ambition; they deſire not to thruſt their fingers into Princes Treaſures, but ſerue them faithfully and honeſtly for their Pay in all their occaſions, when they are required, and who venture their liues and goods with all readineſſe and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:3617:40"/>
for the defence of Iuſtice, and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of violence. In concluſion, this is the Faction that neuer could, can, or will indure ſo many groſſe abuſes and ſeditious practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt our Countrey.</p>
            <p>Theſe perfidious perſons muſt needs haue a feeling (if not in themſelues, yet by others) that all men haue the glory of God, and the truth of their owne Religion in tender re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation, and that euery one thinkes in his owne conſcience, it is a deadly ſinne not to defend it, and reſiſt the Perſecuters thereof: and yet theſe men ſhame not to giue out, and publiſh to the world, that our end is nothing elſe but to perſecute the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Romane Religion, and to driue it out of our Countrey.</p>
            <p>Had the Romane Catholiques alone made this complaint, perchance ſome might haue beleeued them; but why then do they of the reformed Religion complaine, who (as they ſay) are not moleſted? Why then doe both the Religions with hand and heart vnite themſelues in theſe proceedings for defence of their Countrey, and maintenance of their ancient liberties? Why doe both
<pb facs="tcp:3617:40"/>
Religions ſit together in Court of Iuſtice at this preſent, with equity and indifferency to puniſh offenders both Reformed and Romane? But theſe bad men kept long ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret in their boſomes this their calumniati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſlander, till now the water of the Fountaines runnes ſo cleere, as they can no longer by troubling it, diſturbe the peace of our Countrey: and therefore now vpon diſcouery of their perfidious and falſe hearts, they vſe this falſe pretext of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to withdraw our Subiects from their Countries ſeruice, and to draw our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Princes and others, not to further with ſuch zeale as they ought, the good ſucceſſe of theſe our proceedings. Let them giue leaue to the honeſt and good men of our Countrey who are ſtill among vs, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine in this particular of Religion, of whom we firmely beleeue that no one man of either Profeſſion will euer open his lips, becauſe we haue neuer ſuffered in all our proceedings, that the leaſt violence ſhould be vſed to the one, or the other.</p>
            <p>They ſay we haue put to death the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſt of <hi>Sondrio:</hi> To this we anſwere, It is
<pb facs="tcp:3617:41"/>
true, and hee had but iuſtice; yet haue wee not taken away the Benefice, but haue giuen order for another to be choſen in his place, to diſcharge that Office: Nor did we proceed againſt him, for that he was a Prieſt, but for his bloudy deeds, his wicked counſailes, and Treaſons. In like manner the Biſhop of <hi>Coira</hi> ſtands out-lawed and baniſhed, but his Biſhoprick is not aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and another in his ſtead is to haue the poſſeſſion. Beſides, there haue beene mo of the reformed Religion puniſhed, then of Catholiques.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes in theſe our daies, that Religion is vſed as a cloke and pretext for vvicked and nefarious actions, and it is the ordinarie cuſtome of thoſe men to ſerue their turnes with ſuch excuſes, who in their life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation neuer ſhewed any acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Religion at all: nor haue any pretence of truth, to approoue the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie and integritie of their actions.</p>
            <p>We are likewiſe charged to haue deſpiſed and ſet at nought the Maieſties of other Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narches in a barbarous manner, by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing our Faith giuen them, and quitting our
<pb facs="tcp:3617:41"/>
friendſhip and Allyance with them. But we knowing well, that to deſpiſe and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate the ſaid Maieſties is vtterly againſt the Chriſtian Faith; wee doe therefore hold them in all reuerent eſteeme and obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thinke our ſelues much honoured, if we enioy their good fauour and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: yet neither may nor can wee by any meanes approoue the vndiſcreet and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient actions of ſome of their Seruants: we hold them for our Confederates, but we are not tied to them in any ſpeciall duties, or ſeruices not comprized in their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor ſpecified in the Articles of League with vs.</p>
            <p>Who can truely ſay, or charge any Delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or Councell of ours, to haue renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced or broken any League or intelligence we had with others?</p>
            <p>We both in generall and in particular are readie, to maintaine towards all men our Faith, Credit, Honour, Oath, and good cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondencie, and neighbourhood. And albeit ſome Embaſſadours by their vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet carriages haue prouoked vs to iuſt diſpleaſure, yet haue wee no purpoſe to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh
<pb facs="tcp:3617:42"/>
any one point in our interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Leagues with others, or to moleſt and trouble them any way, onely wee could wiſh, that thoſe Miniſters of State were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed a better courſe how to carry them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or elſe that their Maſters would call them home, and ſend others in their place.</p>
            <p>If our People were ſo temerarious and head-ſtrong as theſe calumniators would make the world beleeue; we, adhering to them as Authours of all lewdneſſe, ſhould euery yeere haue made Leagues and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken them, like theſe our ſlanders, who haue wrought their vttermoſt among vs to renounce and quit all our true and reall Confederations, which, by the conſtancie and faithfulneſſe of our People, and ſome of our Heads and Councellours, wee ſtill maintaine in their force and inuiolable: and if any fault hath beene made, or failing in duties whereto wee were obliged by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, the blame is to be laid vpon thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious Patriots, who like Merchants ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelues to be wonne with money, by their falſe ſhadowes and pretences of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:42"/>
to turne our <hi>Common People</hi> from the right way, who hold among vs the ſupreme Authoritie.</p>
            <p>By all which things aforeſaid, wee hope that euery man (eſpecially ſuch as know what true libertie is, and wherein it conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) ſhall haue occaſion for the time to come, to iudge more modeſtly of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without giuing eare to falſe pretences, or fauouring the ſaid perfidious Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of ours, by vs iuſtly baniſhed; but ſhall baniſh them likewiſe out of their limits, as perſons moſt wicked, and deſeruing any kinde of puniſhment.</p>
            <p>GOD, who changeth Kingdomes, ſetteth vp and pulleth downe Kings, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth Dominions, and raiſeth the Humble, keepe in his gracious fauour and protection all States and Common-wealths, defend them from Warre and Treaſon, from ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and iealouſies; confounding all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidious practices by his mightie Power, and preſeruing all good Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by his infinite Mercy.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:3617:43"/>
            <head>AND to the intent that the world may know, how much theſe mercenary men of ours tooke vpon them, by propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and procuring to ſell our Libertie, and Treaſury to Princes and forraine States: we haue ſet downe word by word, the Articles of the League betweene his Maieſty of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and our Countries, to which League they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded our Commons in the yeere <hi>1617.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Articles drawne and to bee agreed vpon</hi> the <hi>9.</hi> of March <hi>1617.</hi> by the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Don Alfonſo Caſale,</hi> Councellor and Embaſsadour for the Catholique Maieſtie in <hi>Switzerland;</hi> in the name and behalfe of the moſt Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Don Pietro di Toledo,</hi> Gouernour of the State of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> on the one party: and the Lords the Heads and Deputies of the Three high Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations Generall of <hi>Griſons</hi> on th other partie: with the good liking and approbation of his Maieſtie, and of the ſaid Three Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations Generall.</p>
            <p>WHereas there hath euer beene a good, ſincere, and faithfull amitie, neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:43"/>
and correſpondencie betweene the Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> and the Three Conſederations Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall; the which, euer ſince the High and Mighty Kings of <hi>Spaine</hi> hau<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beene Lords of that State, hath beene continued by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties: therefore both the parties, vpon dye conſideration of the happineſſe, profit and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, which ariſeth from the good affection, ſinceritie, and louing intelligence betweene them; and to the intent that all cauſe of iealouſie and diffidence might bee remooued, which hath or might heretofore happen betweene the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of <hi>Philip</hi> the third, and the ſaid Three Confederations Generall; and that a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good intelligence, faithfull neighbourhood, and a reall and mutuall vnion might be esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed betweene them: they haue to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory of GOD, and to the publique good and ſafety, ioyntly reſolued to conclude this preſent Capitulation, Treatie, and Vnion, to ſtand in the full force and vertue of a continuall and hereditary League.</p>
            <p>And therefore the moſt Illuſtrious Prince and Lord, <hi>Don Pietro di Toledo</hi> Generall of <hi>Millan,</hi> in the name and behalfe of his Maieſtie, and his ſucceſſors Dukes of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:44"/>
on th' one party, and the High and Noble Lords the Preſidents, Councellors, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalties of the Three Confederations Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall on the other partie, doe promiſe, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene his Maieſtie as Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Subiects of the ſaid Duchy, and the Three Confederations Generall, with all their Subiects in <hi>Valtelina, Bombio,</hi> and the County of <hi>Chiauenna,</hi> ſhall be a true, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, and perpetuall amitie, correſpondencie, neighbourhood, and vnion; ſo at neither par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall ſuffer themſelues to be imployed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any ſeruice or occaſion, to the preiudice and hurt of the other; nor ſhall ſuffer that through their Countreys or their Subiects, any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, counſaile, or aide ſhall bee giuen directly or indirectly, which may ſecretly or openly damnifie either party, but that they ſhall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and reſiſt them with all poſsible diligence and power. And when either of the parties ſhall know or vnderſtand any ſecret practice or attempt, whereby may bee engaged the preiudice and hurt of the other; that then they ſhall without delay giue notice thereof, and procure with all diligence and faithfulneſſe to diuert the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:44"/>
And becauſe his Excellencie vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that the Three Confederations Generall would willingly that the Fort built in the yeere <hi>1603.</hi> vpon the Confines of <hi>Valtelina</hi> were demoliſhed, as a pawne and pledge that they were againe reſtored into the good fauour and aſſured confidence of his Maieſtie; hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, in testimonie of his Maiesties good af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to the Three Confederations Generall, That, ſo ſoone as this ſaid Capitulation ſhall be concluded, ſworne, and ſigned by both the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, forthwith the Fort and Sconce belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to it, ſhall effectually and really be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: and that the ſaid Fort ſhall neuer be re-built, ſo long as the Contents of this Capitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation be faithfully and inuiolably kept, and no ſecond cauſe bee giuen his Maieſtie of diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and doubt of them, as was in the yeere <hi>1603.</hi> And foraſmuch as the ſaid Lords Preſidents, Councellors, and Comminalties of the Three Confederations Generall, doe know that the reaſon of that diffidence and doubt, which cauſed the building of the Fort was, in regard of the League and paſsage granted to the State of <hi>Venice</hi> the yeere before; they therefore promiſe for themſelues and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,
<pb facs="tcp:3617:45"/>
neuer to renew the ſaid League or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, nor to giue their conſent thereunto, ſo long as this Capitulation ſhall continue.</p>
            <p>That commerce, negotiation, and paſſage ſhall bee free through both their Countries, and for all their Subiects without exception of perſons, of what qualitie and condition ſo euer: but with this prouiſo, that in their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of credence there be no ſcandall, nor bring in with them prohibited bookes, and that in time of Peſtilence or Plague, the ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes be obſerued. And concerning the Toll of Cattle or other commodities, which ſhall be brought into the State of <hi>Millan,</hi> they ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the like liberties with thoſe already gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſuch Swiſſe Cantons as are confederate with his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>And in caſe it ſo happen that his Maieſtie ſhall haue neede of the Souldiers of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to defend his Duchy of <hi>Millan,</hi> he ſhall haue a Leauy granted him by the Three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federations Generall, of foure thouſand men at the moſt, and two thouſand at the leaſt, (but all to be voluntaries;) reſeruing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding a power in the Three Confederati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Generall, to grant a greater number at
<pb facs="tcp:3617:45"/>
their pleaſure: The choiſe of the Collonell and Captaines to bee made by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Embaſsadour: who hauing made the ſaid Leauie, hee ſhall agree with the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell and Captaines choſen, for their Armes and Pay.</p>
            <p>And in caſe his Maieſtie would cauſe to paſse into his Duchie of <hi>Millan,</hi> through the Countrey of the Three Confederations Generall, or of their Subiects, any number of forraine Souldiours, for the preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and defence of his Duchy or other his States, free paſſage ſhall bee granted to his Captaines and Officers, ſo as their Troopes conſiſt of no more then two hundred men, and that they bee alwaies diſtant one dayes iourney the one from the other. Euery Troope alſo ſhall haue his Captaine or Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and alſo one Commiſſary appointed by the Three Confederations Generall, at the charge of his Maieſtie, to ſee that good order and diſcipline be kept, for the auoiding of all inconueniences; which Souldiours ſhall pay for their victuals, and other cuſtomes, and ſhall beare themſelues quietly &amp; peaceably through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3617:46"/>
They ſhall beare no other Armes but Sword and Dagger, if they bee on foote; and they on horſebacke, nothing but their Piſtols: and in caſe it ſhall appeare by proofe, that theſe Souldiours haue damniſied the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of the Three Confederations Generall, that then his Maieſtie ſhall be bound to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
            <p>On th' other ſide, if it ſhould ſo happen that the Three Confederations Generall were ſet vpon in hoſtile manner by any Prince, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentate, or free State, that then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie ſhall be bound vpon euery their demand, to ſend to their ſuccours two thouſand foot, and two hundred horſe, vpon his owne expence till the warre bee ended: and in caſe the Three Confederations Generall ſhould ſtand in neede of greater ſuccours, his Maieſtie ſhall be bound to ſend them forthwith: But if the Three Confederations Generall ſhall finde it more for their aduantage, or like it better to have money then Souldiours; that then his Maieſtie ſhall truely pay them ten thouſand Crownes a moneth ſo long as their warre laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and ſhall lend them ſixe Peeces of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerie and Munition thereunto belonging, as
<pb facs="tcp:3617:46"/>
farre as the vttermost bounds of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Chiauenna,</hi> with condition that the warre being done, the Artillerie bee reſtored. It ſhall bee lawfull for the Three Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Generall and their Subiects, to buy at the Faire of <hi>Como</hi> and <hi>Palanza</hi> in the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy of <hi>Millan,</hi> all ſorts of Graine for euery mans vſe and neceſsitie, with like freedome as thoſe Swiſſe-Cantons doe, which are in League with his Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>His Maieſtie as Duke of <hi>Millan,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his wonted Princely Liberalitie, and to teſtifie his gracious fauour to the Three Confederations Generall, promiſeth to pay in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Exchequer of each Confederation Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall yeerely, vpon <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Iohn Baptiſts</hi> day, three thouſand Florens, worth three ſhillings nine pence Sterling a-piece: This paiment to beginne the firſt <hi>Saint Iohn Baptiſts</hi> day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sealing and Swearing of this Vnion.</p>
            <p>And when any difference or diſpute ſhall <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſe betweene his Maieſtie and the Three Confederations Generall, two Arbiters ſhall be choſen of either party, who ſhall meet at <hi>Chiauenna</hi> or <hi>Lorico,</hi> as the one or other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> ſhall be Plaintiffe or Defendant; and theſe
<pb facs="tcp:3617:47"/>
differences betweene them in two moneths to bee cleerely determined and decided. And in caſe any difference ariſe betweene priuate perſons of both the States, that then the Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe ſhall call the Defendant before his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate and Iudge: but in caſe they cannot here be agreed, and their difference compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that then each of the Parties ſhall haue choiſe of one able man well experienced in cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Iuſtice, out of the Aduerſaries Countrey: and then to caſt Lots which of theſe two ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the difference.</p>
            <p>That this preſent Capitulation ſhall bee no way preiudiciall to the League and Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-*Riuerſall, made and giuen by the Three Confederations Generall with the Crowne of France: but that, that League and Letter ſhall ſtill remaine in their force, and their owne proper words.</p>
            <p>That this preſent Capitulation ſhall bee perpetuall and hereditarie; his Maiestie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing on his part the holy Sea of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Sacred Romane Empire, the High and Mighty Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> his League with the Catholique-Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and all other his ancient Leagues and Treaties. And
<pb facs="tcp:3617:47"/>
on the other part, the Three Confederations Generall reſeruing the Sacred Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, their League and Letter-*Riuerſall with the Crowne of <hi>France,</hi> their perpetuall Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the High and Mighty Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> their Confederation with the Cantons of <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and all other their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Leagues which haue beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly inuiolably and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally kept and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
